All beings, in the process of living,
（観察者）
何者も生きていると その過程で
are met by those who stand in the
way of their continued existence.
しばしば
それを妨害する者が現れる
They take and destroy what comprises
them, restricting what they can do.
そのものを構成しているものを奪い
壊し 選択を阻む
I do not think highly of this.
私は これをよく思わない
The freedom to choose is a sacred
thing that ought to be given to all.
選択の自由は誰もが与えられるべき
尊きものである
♪～
～♪
（グーグー）なっ！
うわっ
New Family
Fushi!
フシ！
Gugu! Run!
（フシ）グーグー にげて
あっ
くっ…
Isn't that...
（グーグー）あいつは…
We were attacked by something
unknown in the forest.
（ピオラン）森で得体の知れない
ヤツに襲われたんじゃ
It looked just like a tree.
そいつは木に そっくりじゃった
Run! Hurry!
にげて はやく
No! I want to help you.
（グーグー）
イヤだ！　お前を助けたい！
（グーグー）お…
うわっ
（フシの吠(ほ)え声）
（グーグー）うわあ… ぐっ…
Fushi!
フシ！
（フシの荒い息）
（グーグー）ふんっ！
（フシ）あ…
Yes!
（グーグー）
よっしゃー！　うわっ…
え？　え… うわあああ…
Gugu!
グーグー！
ぐっ…
（グーグー）
うわあ… ぐっ… うう…
うっ… ぐはああ…
（せき込み）
The liquor...
酒が…
Fushi...
フシ…
What am I supposed to do?
俺 一体どうすれば…
Ow, hot!
アチッ
Where'd this fire come from?
なんで火が？
あ！
I get it.
そうか
This fire spread to the liquor I barfed up.
俺が まき散らした酒に
この火が引火して…
I have an idea!
あっ 思いついたぞ！
（グーグーの荒い息）
It's distracted by Fushi right now.
（グーグー）
あいつはフシに気を取られている
Now!
今だ！
I'll bear down on my belly and puke it out.
腹に力を入れて…
一気に吐く！
（息を吐く音）
Huh? Why?
（グーグー）あれ なんで？
It worked so well earlier.
さっきは勢いよく出たのに
ハァ！　ゴホッ…
No... Am I empty?
（グーグー）
まさか… からっぽに？
（フシ）アブない！
（グーグー）うわっ
ぐあっ…
Fushi!
フシ！
Run, or I'll get angry!
にげないと オレ おこる
ダメ ここ！
Leave here!
（グーグー）く…
（フシ）グルルル…
Now!
はやく！
（グーグー）うぐっ
Hang in there. I'll be back in five minutes.
耐えろ！　５分で戻る
No!
Come back, and I'll bite you!
ダメ！　もどったら かむ
Works for me!
（グーグー）上等じゃ！
（グーグーの荒い息）
I'll get back to Booze Man's place in one minute
（グーグー）１分で酒爺(さけじい)の家へ行き
and come back with a
bellyful of liquor in two.
２分で腹に酒をためて戻ってくる
Just wait, Fushi.
待ってろよ フシ！
（グーグー）え？
あ…
Wh-What's wrong?
な… 何だ？
く… んん… がっ！
Right, it's the booze.
（グーグー）そうか 酒のせいで…
Get up.
立て
I have to go.
行くんだ
You're the only one who
can save Fushi, Gugu!
フシを助けられるのは
お前だけなんだぞ！
グーグー！
（グーグーの荒い息）
That's it. Go.
（グーグー）そうだ 行け
Good.
いいぞ
You're almost there...
もう…
少しだ！
（リーン）あ！
You're the one who was with Rean-sama.
（雇われ男）お前だな
リーン様と一緒にいたのは
What?
（リーンの母）え？
（リーンの父）なに！
Were you the one who swindled my daughter?
君なのか
うちの娘をそそのかしたのは？
I told you!
さっきから言ってるでしょ！
I left home on my own!
私が勝手に家出したの
They have nothing to do with it!
この人たちは関係ないって！
You! What did you do to my daughter?
（父）君！　うちの子に何をした？
I'm sorry. I didn't think Dad
would come all the way here.
ごめんね パパたちが
ここまで来るとは思わなかったの
（グーグー）ん…
Let's leave it be, dear.
もういいじゃない あなた
遅くなってしまうわ
It's getting late.
（グーグー）ふわぁ…
What's the matter, Gugu?
どうした？
グーグー 様子がヘンじゃぞ
Something seems off about you.
（グーグー）うえっ
Gimme some booze, old man!
ハァ… じーしゃん 酒くれ！
Something really strong!
うんと強(つえ)えやつをな！
（酒爺）はあ？
ああ…
あ…
（２人）ああ…
（グーグー）ウイ～ フヒヒヒ…
You want booze?
酒をくれだと？
What's gotten into you, Gugu?
どうしちまったんだ グーグー？
What do you think?
（グーグー）
どうもこうも 俺の腹の酒が
The booze in my belly's all gone!
からっぽに なっちまったんだよ！
And don't give me just any booze.
いいか ただの酒じゃねえぞ！
Give me the strongest shit!
一番やべえ酒を出せ！
What a horrible boy!
まあ！　なんて子なの
I want the best shit!
Hey! What's wrong with you?
ちょっと どうしちゃったの？
What happened? Where's Fushi-san?
何があったの？　フシさんは？
（グーグー）へ？
Fushi's in the forest, like, boom!
フシは森でドーン！
Vwoom, vwoom!
ブオンブオンなの
So I have to get right back.
だから俺 すぐ戻らなきゃ
Old man, let me take care of this.
爺さん ここは わしに任せて
Do as he says. Don't ask any questions.
黙ってグーグーの言うとおりに
するんじゃ
A-All right.
うん 分かった
This liquor's been distilled over and over.
（酒爺）
これは何度も何度も蒸留した⸺
It's the strongest we have.
うちの店で一番強い酒だ
（グーグー）うえっ
（むせる声）
I thought so.
やはりな どこか
破損しておるのかもしれん
There might be a rupture somewhere.
You need to do something
about it, or you'll die.
このままでは死ぬぞ
A bit late for that!
（グーグー）どの口が今しゃら！
Hurry up and pour it in me!
さっさと入れやがれ！
Hurry up!
ほら 早く！
We're leaving, Rean.
（母）帰りますよ リーン
えっ イヤ！　私 ここがいいの！
No! I like it here!
That's enough.
（母）いいかげんにしなさい
ここの人にも迷惑だわ
You're causing trouble for
the people here, too.
She throws tantrums when
she doesn't get her way.
（父）
自分の思いどおりにならないと⸺
かんしゃくを起こす子なんです
That's why she left home, too.
家出するのも そう
But it's not a problem.
ですが問題はありません
Don't you think the problem is that
you don't see a problem with that?
問題ではないと思っているところが
問題なのでは？
（父）あ…
Come, let's go.
さあ 帰るんだ
No! I'm not going home!
イヤ！　帰らない！
Stop being selfish!
（父）わがままを言うんじゃない
（リーン）イヤ 放して！
No! Let me go!
（父）ん？
You can't go home.
（グーグー）帰っちゃダメらあ
This is none of your business.
君には関係ない うせたまえ
Begone!
You just can't go!
（グーグー）何が何でも らーめ！
I said no!
とにかくダメらの！
Just what is your complaint?
（グーグー）あ…
（父）一体 何が不満なんだ？
Haven't we done everything to make
sure you can become a proud adult?
私たちは
お前が将来 恥をかかないよう
尽くしてきたつもりだが
That's exactly it!
（リーン）それよ！
（父）ん？
I want more freedom.
私は もっと自由に…
ヘタに生きたいのよ
I want to live more clumsily.
So clumsily that it's embarrassing.
恥ずかしくなっちゃうほどにね！
All right. I get it.
分かった あれでしょう
You didn't like that we chose
who you're going to marry.
勝手に結婚相手を決められたのが
イヤだったんでしょ？
N-No!
（リーン）ハッ ち… 違うわ
（グーグー）
ヌハハハ… ホントに？
Seriously?
Rean-san already has a husband lined up?
リーンしゃん
結婚相手 もう決まってんの？
No, that's, um...
いや それは その…
I don't know who the guy is,
（グーグー）
どこの誰か知らねえけど
but the one who loves Rean-san
the most is me, Gugu.
リーンしゃんを一番愛してるのは
この俺… グーグーだかりゃ
え？
Anyway, I'm going now.
（グーグー）んじゃ 俺 行く
あと よろしく！
Deal with it!
We're leaving, too.
私たちも帰るぞ
（母･リーン･父）あっ
（２人）ああ…
（グーグーの荒い息）
Fushi! I'm back!
（グーグー）フシ 戻ったぞ！
Where's the enemy?
敵は どこだ？
Fushi...
フシ？
（うなり声）
（木々が折れる音）
You're safe, Fushi!
（グーグー）無事だったか フシ！
No.
あっ 違う… フシじゃない
That's not Fushi.
Fushi, where are you?
（グーグー）
フシ どこへ？　フシ！
Fushi!
（威嚇する声）
Where did you take Fushi?! You bastard!
（グーグー）
フシをどこへやった？　この野郎！
うわっ く…
Give Fushi back!
フシを返せ！
（鳴き声）
（グーグー）あ…
（うなり声）
（グーグー）うわっ うわあああ…
What do you think you're doing?
何のマネですか？　どいてください
Out of the way, please.
（グーグー）くっ
（うなり声）
スゥ… フーッ！
ん？
（一同）あっ！
I've got more!
（叫び声）
（グーグー）まだまだ！
（息を吐く音）
（苦しむ声）
It's burning...
（雇われ男）
燃えてる… 燃えてるぞ！
It's burning!
Gugu...
グーグー
Fushi... Where did you go?
（グーグー）
フシ どこ行ったんだ？
Are you broken?
食われちまったのかよ
不死身のくせに…
I thought you were immortal.
く…
I had so much fun with you here.
お前がいてくれた おかげで
楽しかったのに
I was so happy.
うれしかったのに…
You made me feel like it's okay to be me.
俺は俺でいいんだって
ちょっと思えたのに
I'm sorry, Fushi.
ごめん フシ 無力な兄貴で…
I'm sorry I'm such a useless brother.
ん？
That light...
あの光は？
おっ
A rock?
石…
My goodness, Fushi.
（観察者）やれやれ
フシよ お前は幸運だ
You're a lucky one.
That being—brittle, but in no way weak—
will make you even stronger.
もろいが決して弱くない存在が
お前を さらに
強くしてくれるだろう
In time.
じきに…
（グーグー）うわっ
う… ぐえっ
Fushi!
フシ！
I took down the enemy.
敵は もう倒したよ 俺が
I did.
Really?
ホント？
Yeah!
（グーグー）うん！
ヘヘッ
That hurts, you ass!
なっ 痛(いて)えぞ この野郎！
（グーグーの笑い声）
Thank you, Gugu.
ありがとオ グーグー
They're back!
帰ってきた！
Hey, what happened?
ねえ 何があったの？
Nothing.
（グーグー）何も！
（酒爺）おおっ さすがグーグー
That's my Gugu!
フヒィ！　食らい尽くしてやるわ
I'm going to demolish this!
Yum!
うまい！　やっぱグーグーの
メシは最高じゃ！
Gugu always makes the best food!
Thanks for coming back.
戻ってきてくれて ありがとう！
You've forgiven me, have you?
俺のこと 許してくれたんだな？
No, I haven't.
（グーグー）いや 許さない
ええ？
I'm not calling you Booze Man anymore.
（グーグー）
だから これからは酒爺ではなく
I'm calling you Booze Shithead.
酒クソじじいって呼ばせてもらう
Ouch...
ガーン…
But you saved my life.
（グーグー）
でも それ以前に命の恩人だ
So I'll drop the "shithead" part
and just call you Booze Man.
だから“クソ”を取って
酒じじいって呼ばせてもらう
G-Gugu...
グ… グーグー
Hey! Don't talk to your elders that way.
こら！　お年寄りの方に向かって
“じじい”なんて呼ぶんじゃない
S-Sorry.
（グーグー）す… すみません
You know, dear...
ねえ あなた
あの子 なかなか やるわよ
That boy's pretty good.
He's better than our chef.
うちのコックより優秀だわ
ん？
Oh, my.
なんてことだ！
Hey, Gugu?
ねえ グーグー
（グーグー）えっ？
Where did Fushi-san go?
フシさんは どうしたの？
Oh, I asked him to get some water.
（グーグー）
あ… 水くみを頼んでる
He should be back soon.
そろそろ来るよ
Fushi, leave this place.
（観察者）フシよ
この場から離れなさい
Why?
なんで？
There is a way for you to become stronger.
（観察者）
お前には より強くなる方法がある
It's to not stay in the same spot.
それは同じ場所に
とどまらないことだ
I don't get it.
いみ わからない
The Nokkers, as I've decided to call them...
（観察者）“ノッカー”
私はヤツらを そう呼ぶことにした
They are plotting the
destruction of this world.
ノッカーは
この世界の崩壊をもくろむ存在だ
They learn.
ヤツらは学習する
They may have lost this time, but they'll
take steps to ensure they win next time.
今回 負けたなら
次回 勝てるよう手を打ってくる
In your current state, you will surely lose.
今の お前では確実に勝てない
It'll take your insides again,
and you'll return to moss and rock.
今回のように中身を奪われて
苔(こけ)や石ころに戻るのだ
You understand, don't you?
分かるだろう？
Gugu will defeat the enemy.
てきは グーグーが たおしてくれる
Gugu is strong.
グーグー つよい
I need Gugu.
オレには グーグー ひつよう
はなれない！
I'm staying.
That, too, is an option.
（観察者）それも また よかろう
If you want to see the end,
I won't stop you.
最後を見届けたいなら
止めはしない
Fushi.
（グーグー）フシ？
（フシ）ん？
What's going on? You've been talking
to yourself this whole time.
（グーグー）
何だよ さっきから独り言なんて
This isn't like you.
らしくないぞ
You don't see?
みえてない？
See what?
（グーグー）何が？
Just get in here already.
てか 早く上がってこい
Everyone's eating already.
みんな もう食ってるぞ
（グーグー）えっ 帰る？
You're going home?!
Yes.
ええ 長いこと お世話になったわ
I appreciate all you've done.
A-Are you sure, though?
（グーグー）で… でも いいの？
I mean... with your parents and all...
あの… ご両親のこと
Well, they're not going to budge
from here until I go home with them.
だって 私が帰るまで
ここからテコでも動かないつもりよ
Besides, I don't even care anymore
それに…
もう どうでもよくなったの
自分の境遇が
about my own situation.
It seems the two of us
have one thing in common.
（グーグー）どうやら俺たちには
１つだけ共通点があるみたいだ
The people who keep us alive
aren't necessarily good people.
自分を生かしてくれる人が
必ずしも いいヤツじゃない
But we aren't so weak that we can't endure it.
でも… それに耐えられないほど
弱くない
See you again, Old Man,
Old Lady, Fushi, Mr. Shopboy.
じゃあ またね
おじいさん おばあさん フシさん
店員さん！
（グーグー）えっ 店員？
Shopboy?
I'm kidding, Gugu.
フフッ 冗談よ グーグー
（酒爺）フフフッ
Well, time to set up shop.
さあて 開店準備だ
I'm going back to sleep.
（ピオラン）
わしは今日は もう寝る
Right, Gugu...
（フシ）そうだ グーグー
Yeah? What is it?
（グーグー）ん？　何だ？
Teach me to cook.
（フシ）オレに りょうり おしえて
What's up? Do you look up to me now?
（グーグー）おっ 急に どうした？
俺に憧れたか？
Welcome.
（グーグー）らっしゃい
Give me what I got last time.
（男性Ａ）前のと同じものを
Can I try a sip of that?
（男性Ｂ）それ 少し味見できる？
Of course.
（グーグー）もちろん
The booze here's gotten good, huh?
（男性Ａ）
ここの酒 おいしくなったよね
Thank you.
（グーグー）ありがとうございます
You've been here for a
while now, haven't you?
（男性Ｂ）君も ここ長いよね？
How many years has it been?
もう何年になる？
うーん… ４年だっけ？
Four years, was it?
Yes.
（グーグー）はい
Gugu, give me a hand.
グーグー ちと手伝ってくれい
Why did you put it all the way up here?
（グーグー）
こんな高い所に置くから
Why did you stuff so many together?
（グーグー）
こんなに たくさん入れるから
You've gotten pretty strong, huh?
お前 力持ちになったな
You were so tiny when you came here.
ここへ来たときは
こんなに小(ち)っこかったのに
Why am I me?
（グーグー）
なんで僕は僕なんだろう？
I guess that's a question I used to have.
なんて思ってたっけ 前は
I hated myself back then.
あの頃は自分のことが嫌いだった
And how do you feel now, Gugu,
about yourself four years later?
今は どうだ グーグー？
４年後の お前は…
Hello.
ごめんください
H-Hey, Rean. Running away from home again?
（グーグー）や… やあ リーン
また家出かい？
Yup, the second time this month.
うん 今月２回目
What's your excuse this time?
（グーグー）今回の言い訳は何？
I heard Fushi-san's interested in needlework.
フシさん
縫い物に興味があるんですって
So I brought a bunch of stuff from home.
だから家から
いろいろ持ってきたの
Fushi's making lunch right now.
（グーグー）
フシなら昼メシ作ってるよ
Upstairs, then?
じゃあ ２階ね
It looks delicious.
（リーン）おいしそう！
Fushi-san's gotten so good at cooking.
ホントに上手になったわね
フシさん
You should stay and eat.
（グーグー）
よかったら食べてってよ
Is Fushi not here?
フシ いないのか？
Fushi went to go wash up.
フシなら水浴びに行っとるぞ
Come on, old woman! You can't
start eating on your own!
（グーグー）バアさん
また１人で勝手に食べ始めてる！
I keep telling you to wait
until we're all at the table!
みんなが そろってからって
いつも言ってるじゃないか
Shut up!
うるしゃい！　グータラしとったら
メシが冷めるじゃろが
The food's going to go cold if I wait!
（フシ）ん？
あ…
Come on, Fushi, hurry up.
（グーグー）おい フシ 早くしろ
みんなでメシ食うぞ
We're all eating.
Yeah, I'll be right there.
うん 今行く
What were you staring at so intently?
（グーグー）
何を熱心に見てたんだ？
Pop all those zits.
吹き出物は どんどん つぶせ
No, there's hair growing on my chin.
いや… アゴから毛が生えてて…
A beard?
（グーグー）おっ ヒゲか！
It's like I'm growing up.
（フシ）まるで大人だ
Yeah. Congrats, Fushi.
（グーグー）ああ おめでとう フシ
♪～
～♪
Preview
Four years have passed since
the battle with the Nokkers.
（観察者）ノッカーとの死闘から
４年の歳月が流れた
But the peace is short-lived.
しかし 平和な暮らしは
長くは続かない
Gugu's lost brother, Shin, emerges,
生き別れたグーグーの兄
シンの来訪を機に
setting in motion the wheels
of Gugu and Rean's fates.
グーグーとリーンの運命の歯車も
Gift From the Past
少しずつ回り始める